Okay, moving on to nephritic syndrome.
The hallmark of nephritic syndrome is glomerular inflammation
and bleeding from the glomerulus.
Now, these patients can have limited proteinuria.
It's usually less than 3.5 grams per day.
That helps to distinguish this from nephrotic syndrome.
The patients can get oliguria, which is a decrease in urine production,
along with azotemia, which is an increase in nitrogenous waste products within the blood.
There is some salt retention.
The retention of salt will also result in the retention of fluid,
which can then result in edema, particularly around the eyes.
And that's because the minimal edema that develops particularly shows itself
in the loose connective tissue around the eyes.
In addition, because there's salt retention and fluid retention,
the patients develop hypertension.
Now, of course, I mentioned that a hallmark was glomerular bleeding,
and one of the key signs of glomerular bleeding will be the presence of red blood cell casts.
The idea here is that if this is the glomerulus, and the glomerulus is bleeding,
so you've got red blood cells coming into the tubules,
the red blood cells will get casted in the shape of the tubule,
and then will be urinated out as this sort of square cast made up of red blood cells.
And again, that's because it gets casted in the shape of the tubule.
So red blood cell casts is a sign of glomerular bleeding.
Now, if a biopsy were to be performed,
we would see a hypercellular inflamed glomerulus.
And remember that I told you that the hallmark was glomerular inflammation.
Important to note that this inflammation is usually driven by the deposition of immune complexes.
The immune complexes activate complement,
and one of the byproducts of complement is C5A.
Remember that C5A attracts neutrophils,
and the neutrophils then mediate the damage,
and that's why you get the hypercellularity in the glomerulus.
Here's a glomerulus from a patient with nephratic syndrome,
and we can see that there are way too many cells within the glomerulus,
and in addition, it's swollen, and it's filling most of Bowman's space.
The prototypic disorder that results in nephratic syndrome
is called post-strep glomerular nephritis.
Now, this is a nephratic syndrome that arises after a group A beta-hemolytic strep infection
of either the skin or the pharynx.
In particular, it occurs with nephratogenic strains.
So there are particular strains of group A beta-hemolytic strep
that carry a M protein virulence factor
that increases the risk of the development of nephritic syndrome.
And so, again, it's important to note
that the M protein virulence factor
is what defines the nephratogenic strains.
It's also important to note that you can get a nephritic syndrome
after infection with non-strep organisms as well.
However, prototypically, it occurs after a group A beta-hemolytic strep infection.
The classic presentation of PSGN
occurs two to three weeks after infection.
The patients present with hematuria, giving them a cola-colored urine.
And they can also develop oliguria, hypertension, and periorbital edema,
as I've already explained.
Again, it's usually seen in children, but it can also occur in adults.
On biopsy, you would see a hypercellular inflamed glomerulus.
Again, this is mediated by immune complex deposition,
so there would be a granular immunofluorescence.
And one of the hallmarks of this disorder
is that you have a sub-epithelial hump on electron microscopy.
Here's a picture of the EM.
This is a large sub-epithelial hump.
Notice that it's sitting on top of the basement membrane,
and this is where the epithelial cells would normally sit.
Now, actually, what happens in this disorder
is that the immune complexes actually start sub-endothelial,
and then they slowly work their way up,
and as they work their way up through this tri-layer,
they then pile up sub-epithelial.
And eventually what's going to happen is
this deposit will simply just dissipate into this space and disappear.
And that helps me to remember
that the treatment is actually supportive.
You don't need to do anything.
The deposits will simply just pass their way through and then disappear.
Now, in most children, the disease will actually resolve,
and they rarely progress to renal failure.
However, adults do have a chance of progressing to renal failure,
and one of the feared complications
is something called rapidly progressive glomerulonephritis.
Now, rapidly progressive glomerulonephritis
is a nephritic syndrome
that progresses to renal failure in weeks to months.
When a patient comes in with rapidly progressive glomerulonephritis
and they've got signs and symptoms of a nephritic syndrome
and appear to be developing rapid renal failure,
a biopsy will be performed.
Now, the biopsy is characterized by crescents in Bowman's space.
And it's very important to note,
for the purposes of board exams,
that the crescent is made up of fibrin and macrophages.
Here's a picture of the glomerulus with the crescent.
Now, here I'm outlining for you the crescent,
and so this represents the crescent.
Here is the normal glomerulus.
Now, examiners like you to know
that this stuff here in the crescent
actually is fibrin and macrophages,
so it's inflammatory debris.
And that's particularly high yield.
It's not collagen, etc.
It is macrophages and fibrin.
Now, when a patient has rapidly progressive glomerulonephritis,
the next thing that you're going to do after biopsy
is immunofluorescence.
And the immunofluorescence will help you,
along with the clinical picture,
to resolve the etiology.
So there's three possibilities
concerning the immunofluorescence.
The first possibility is that you get something
called the linear immunofluorescence.
Now, the idea here is that you've got
these endothelial cells,
you've got the basement membrane,
and then, of course, you've got your podocytes.
If there is a linear immunofluorescence,
then that means that you have an antibody
against the glomerular basement membrane.
This antibody then binds
the glomerular basement membrane,
creating a sharp line on immunofluorescence,
which is called a linear immunofluorescence.
Now, the key disease in which you see that
is Good-Pasture syndrome.
Of course, in Good-Pasture syndrome,
you have an antibody against the collagen
in both the glomerular
and the alveolar basement membranes.
And so these patients will present with hematuria
due to the renal involvement,
and they'll present with hemoptysis
due to the pulmonary involvement.
It classically arises in a young adult male.
Now, another possibility would be
to have a granular immunofluorescence.
And you're well aware of the fact
that when you have a granular immunofluorescence,
you've got immune complex deposition.
The most common cause
if there's a granular immunofluorescence
would be post-strep glomerulonephritis.
And that's particularly important to note.
Again, in PSGN,
you've got antigen-antibody complexes
which are depositing,
which then cause the disease.
Another very high-yield cause
if you had a granular immunofluorescence
would be something called
diffuse-proliferative glomerulonephritis.
Now, in diffuse-proliferative glomerulonephritis,
you get deposition of antigen-antibody complexes
that are sub-endothelial,
underneath the endothelial cell.
And what's very high-yield to note here
is that this is the most common type of renal disease
that you would see in lupus.
Remember that in lupus patients,
the most common cause of death is renal failure,
and that the most common disease
that damages the kidney
is diffuse-proliferative glomerulonephritis,
giving you a nephritic syndrome,
and sometimes giving you
a rapidly progressive glomerulonephritis.
Now, it's also important to remember
that if a patient with lupus
presents with nephrotic syndrome,
remember that the cause of nephrotic syndrome
in lupus patients
is going to be membranous nephropathy.
Again, that's high-yield as well.
Now, finally,
if you have a negative immunofluorescence,
then they call that posse-immune.
Posse-immune means limited immune,
i.e. you really don't have anything significant
on immunofluorescence.
And so the next step in posse-immune cases
will be to perform something called an ANCA,
antineutrophil cytoplasmic antibody.
Let's go back and remind ourselves
that when you perform the ANCA test,
you have a slide with a neutrophil on it.
Now, when you take the patient's serum
and you introduce it to this slide,
the antibodies in the patient's serum
can either bind adjacent to the nucleus,
or they can bind out here in the cytoplasm.
If they bind adjacent to the nucleus,
then that is called
a perinuclear antineutrophil cytoplasmic.
Antibody, or a P-ANCA.
If they bind out here in the cytoplasm,
then that is called
a cytoplasmic antineutrophil cytoplasmic antibody.
And, of course, in a posse-immune case,
the ANCA becomes particularly important.
The reason why is that patients
who have a C-ANCA
will have Wegner's granulomatosis.
Now, in Wegner's granulomatosis,
remember that you classically get involvement
of the lung, giving you hemoptysis,
and you also get involvement of the kidney,
giving you rapidly progressive glomerulonephritis.
But remember from our discussion of the vasculidities
that Wegner's granulomatosis is that C disease.
If you remember, I told you about the C mnemonic.
And so it's not only going to involve the lung
and the kidney,
but it's also going to involve the nasopharynx.
Now, this is very important for board examinations.
When a patient comes in with hemoptysis,
and they come in with hematuria,
and they've got a rapidly progressive glomerulonephritis
with crescents,
the knee-jerk is to think
that they have Goodpasture syndrome,
because that's sort of the one
that we classically remember.
However, you need to be aware
that if the patient also has nasal symptoms,
nasopharyngeal symptoms like sinusitis,
they could tell you, for example, on the exam
that the patient also has a history
of sinus infections or sinusitis.
Then you really need to think about the fact
that you may be dealing with Wegner's granulomatosis,
because sinusitis or sinus problems
would not be seen in Goodpasture syndrome.
And, of course, the C-ANCA and the immunofluorescence
would help to distinguish this,
because you would have a linear immunofluorescence
in Goodpastures,
but you would have no immunofluorescence,
but instead a C-ANCA in Wegner's granulomatosis.
Now, if the patient has a P-ANCA,
then there's two possibilities.
One possibility would be microscopic polyangiitis,
and the other possibility would be Churg-Strauss.
Now, what's important to note
is that in Churg-Strauss,
you're going to have three things
that you will not have in microscopic polyangiitis.
Number one, you'll have granulomatous inflammation.
That's not seen in microscopic polyangiitis,
but is seen in Churg-Strauss.
Number two, you'll have eosinophilia,
which, again, would only be seen in Churg-Strauss.
And number three, you'll have asthma.
And again, that would only be seen in Churg-Strauss.
And so, these are three important distinctions
that you should note
when you're trying to make the difference
between Churg-Strauss and microscopic polyangiitis,
again, both giving you a P-ANCA.
Here's a picture of the linear immunofluorescence.
Notice that you've got immunofluorescence,
but it contains these very sharp green lines.
And so, this would be an indication
that you're most likely dealing with Goodpasture syndrome.
Okay, moving on to IgA nephropathy.
This is the most common cause of nephropathy worldwide.
In this particular case,
IgA immune complex deposits
in the mesangium of the glomeruli.
And so, this is what it looks like.
You get deposition in the mesangium,
but the most important is that this is IgA.
And so, nothing else that we've covered
would give you IgA deposition in the kidney.
This is gonna present during childhood
with episodic growth or microscopic hematuria.
You'll have RBC casts.
Of course, if the glomerulus bleeds,
then you're gonna have casting of the RBCs.
And it usually follows mucosal infections.
Now, the idea here is
when you get a mucosal infection,
you end up producing excess IgA
to try to defend yourself
against that mucosal infection.
So, every time you get a mucosal infection,
you produce a ton of IgA.
Some of that IgA goes into the mesangium.
It deposits as immune complexes
within the mesangium.
And then, that's gonna result
in the glomerular bleeding.
Now, of course, it's episodic
because as the mucosal infection resolves,
you decrease the IgA.
And so, the hematuria goes away.
And then, the next time
you get a mucosal infection,
you again get another episode
of bleeding from the kidney.
This can then slowly progress
to renal failure.
I've already mentioned the fact
that you're gonna have
IgA immune complex deposition
in the mesangium.
Alport syndrome is an inherited defect
in type 4 collagen.
It's most commonly X-linked.
And what happens here
is that you get thinning and splitting
of the glomerular basement membrane.
Now, when that occurs,
that's gonna result in isolated hematuria.
You're only gonna have hematuria.
But again, that's one of the hallmarks
of nephritic syndrome.
Now, the patients can also have
sensory herring loss
because the basement membrane
can be damaged in this region
along with ocular disturbances
also due to damage
of the basement membrane.
And so, it's these three key findings
along with a family history
that clue you in to Alport syndrome.
Isolated hematuria,
sensory herring loss,
and ocular disturbances
in a family.
And so, that concludes our section
on nephritic syndrome.
Let's go.
We'll open up.